Mariano Riva Palacio Collection:
University of Texas at Austin
- Enero-Junio 1850
  - 4081 Rubio, Mucio. [Carta a Antonio Sein.] Ixmiquilpan, April 16, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Circulation of government circular refuting the newspaper article; peacefulness of the Indians; case of assault on cura of Chilcuautla by Lic. Tranquilino Valera; Administrador Arévalo; tax collection in Alfajayucan and El Cardenal.
  - 4082 Martínez, José A. [Carta a Antonio Sein.] Actopan, April 17, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Protest against newspaper article dedicated to the Indians.
  - 4083 Villaseñor, Alejandro. Cuernavaca, April 17, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Protest against newspaper article opposing the government; fear of political results; Ixtla; Cocoyotla; Tetecala; Pepita; invitation to dance; San Gabriel; Tianguis.
  - 4084 Lebrija, Manuel María. Mexico, April 17, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Account of illness; report of social activities in Toluca; Calle de Cordobanes; the Tobacco problem; Elorriaga.
  - 4085 Barrientos, José María. Vicario Capitular del Arzobispado de México, Mexico, April 17, 1850. LS. 2 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Protest against newspaper articles; promise of aid in conjunction with the Junta eclesiástica de Censura; dangers of comunismo y socialismo; letters to Vicarios foráneos and parishes of the state, assuring Indians of equal rights and their duty of obedience to law.
  - 4086 Arizcorreta, Mariano. April 18, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request that decree establishing Santa Anna and Xochicoatlán as a municipalidad be withheld pending an interview with a committee favoring establishment of municipalidades in Santa Anna Tianguistenco, Xochicoatlán. and Caluali; support of Cura Ignacio Ángeles, Distrito de Huejutla; Prefecto Andrade.
  - 4087 Calderón, Lorenzo. Sultepec, April 19, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Collection of the capitation tax; return from Zacualpam; Temascaltepec.
  - 4088 Iturbe, Francisco. Mexico, April 20, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Toll on Cuautitlán road; road improvements; protest against newspaper article.
  - 4089 Lezama, Juan. Tulancingo, April 20, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Opposition of soldiers to capitation tax; collection of the tax.
  - 4090 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, April 20, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Transmittal of anonymous letter; warning of precautions needed.
  - 4091 Sein, Antonio. Tula, April 20, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Settlement of dispute between Mixquiahuala and haciendas de Cortina; need to sow the fields; Copca; Gil; circulation of a denunciation by the state of newspaper article arousing the Indians; effects in Ixmiquilpan and Actopan; collection of tax; objection to Tomás Andrade as school inspector; school closed in Atitalaquia.
  - 4092 Piedra, Epigmenio de la. Tenancingo, April 21, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Efforts to free the piece of marble at La Cautera; efforts of Monroy to move it to a workshop to begin cutting; design for a statue.
  - 4093 Primo de Rivera, Joaquín. [Carta a los Señores Vocales de la Junta menor de arbitrios para el reedificio de la Capilla del Smo. Cristo de Santa Teresa.] Gobierno eclesiástico del Arzobispado de México, April 21, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 28 cm.
    Appointment of committee of Germán Landa, Manuel Tejada, Juan F. Pacheco, Andrés Cervantes, and Rafael Díaz.
  - 4094 Barquera, Mucio. Huichapan, April 21, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for employment of ex-Administrador Moreno; danger of the cholera.
  - 4095 Cruz, Agustín. Mexico, April 22, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Departure of Lagardo; escort furnished by General Quijano; departure of Oliveros and Capitán Silverio Camacho; capture of alleged robber Góngora; Alonso Rodríguez; plants brought from Huam[]o; Escudero.
  - 4096 Pérez Palacios, Ángel. Cuernavaca, April 23, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Note of Lacunza on road improvement; meeting with Tiburcio Gómez de la Madrid, Ramón Cano, Ventura Orellana, and Ignacio Silva; collection of tax; opening of road to Yautepec and Morelos; settlement of claims from U.S. occupation; Lieutenant Colonel of Engineers Cano; arrest of Salgado.
  - 4097 Gómez Pedraza, Manuel. Sacro y Nacional Monte de Piedad de Ánimas, Mexico, April 23, 1850. LS. 2 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Recommendation for José María León for position as Administrador general de Coches del Sitio; long service with the Ayuntamiento; Juliana; Quevedo.
  - 4098 Borbolla, Ramón de. Huasca, April 23 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Complaint about Indian rights; Mariano López; Indian relations with the Church; vicario capitular; meetings in Mexico; Antonio Ruiz; Escalerillas and Reloj Streets; Address at Mineral del Monte.
  - 4099 Cervantes, Miguel. Mexico, April 23, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Interest in road to Texcoco; Cuevas; Campero; travel of Captain Antonio Dasa to Toluca; Obispo Belaunzarán.
  - 4100 Castañeda, Marcelino. Ministerio de Estado y del Despacho de Justicia y Negocios Eclesiásticos, Mexico, April 29, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Recommendation for Antonio Daza in suit against Juan Ortega, Administrador de Mextitlán and Zumpango; Mariano Monterde.
  - 4101 Díez de Sollano, José María. Mexico, April 23, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Request for support of Madrid against Barrientos in Church controversy; work of Cabildo eclesiástico; Dr. Garza, Subiria, Becerra; extra lessons for Carlos.
  - 4102 De la Trouplinière, C. Toluca. April 25, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Illness; plans for surveying roadway from Tenango to Ixtla; need for assistant; Rayón; Morelia; Fuentes.
  - 4103 García, Juan M. Chalco, April 25, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Celebration of the Bases Orgánicas; expenditures for celebration; extra requirements; toll on canoe travel; efforts to collect from Primitivo Martínez.
  - 4104 Calderón, Lorenzo. Sultepec, April 26, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Reaction to article in newspaper Temis No. 2; search for Aguilar; opposition to tax collection in Ayuntamiento; water rights; suspicions of Antolín; León.
  - 4105 Fonseca, J. Urbano and José María Díez de Sollano. Mexico, April 26, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for intervention with Atilano Sánchez for donation from the Obras pías to help school expenses; support by Gregorio Mier y Terán; Bustillos.
  - 4106 Roldán, Benito. Tecozautla, April 27, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Transmittal of legal papers with request for help in obtaining a position.
  - 4107 Pérez Palacios, Ángel. Cuernavaca, April 27, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Appointment to Junta for road inspection accepted; study of the Tianguistengo road; estimated income from tolls on Acapulco road; arrival of De La Trouplinière; Ixtla road; precautions against cholera; Lic. Aparicio; $125,000 assigned the district; article in Temis; road to Yautepec; Plan de Amilpas; arrest of Salgado; Barrio; Ventura Orellana.
  - 4108 León, Esteban V. Tem[]c, April 27, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Return from Zacualpan; Miguel Salgado in Teloloapan; watch over secret operations; safety of road to Toluca; need for pay; Calderón.
  - 4109 Villar, José del. Coyoacán, April 27, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Precautions against cholera; secret gambling; Ramírez.
  - 4110 Villaseñor, Alejandro. Cuernavaca, April 28, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Organization of health commission; precautions against cholera; toll collection on roads to Santiago Tianguistengo and to Mexico; road to Ixtla and Morelos; help of Rovalo, Goribar, and Goyoneche; newspaper article; resignation of Silva; illness.
  - 4111 Piedra, Epigmenio de la. Tenancingo, April 29, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Plans of Monroy and Escultor Solachi to begin work on the piece of marble; regulation concerning cholera.
  - 4112 Otero, Mariano. Mexico, April 29, 1850. ALS., 3 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Newspaper article; “Emilio 20”; efforts of Barajas to settle suit between Rodríguez and Maneyro; suit over value of some books and pictures; death of Rodríguez; Cumplido; prices in Paris catalog; Yáñez; plans for use of part of the U.S. indemnity; aduanas marítimas.
  - 4113 Álvarez, Juan. Guerrero, April 29, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Antonio Antolín and Ramón Aguilar accused of fomenting sedition among the Indians; plans for stopping them; distribution of printed pamphlets; Cantú.
  - 4114 Salgado, Miguel. Mexico, April 30, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Denial of charges of fomenting guerra de castas in Cuernavaca and Ixtla area; Benito Haro; work in farming and mining in Teloloapam, Cerro del Gallo, and Fronteras de Tepatitlán; mines recommended by Almonte; interview in Iguala; Tequesquite; Juez de Buenavista; meeting with Director del Archivo General; search in the Libros de Mercedes for land titles; Juez de Huajintlán; Director Miguel Arriola; recommendation of Juan Álvarez; record of arrest.
  - 4115 Barrio, Juan N. del. Mexico, May 1, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Plan of Ángel [Pérez Palacios?] for road improvements; Juan Goribar; Distrito de Cuernavaca.
  - 4116 Sein, Antonio. Tula, May 1, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Javier Lagarde, Comandante de la Seguridad pública of Tula District; measures against cholera; symptoms described; Jilotepec; Acambay; Tepetitlán; illness in Arroyozarco reported by Dr. Joaquín Navarro; receipt of medicinal herb called Yerba del Indio, grown in Chapa and Mota; epidemic of 1833; shortage of arms.
  - 4117 Álvarez, Juan. Guerrero, May 1, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Meeting in San Gabriel; help given by Gómez; arrest of Salgado; constructive work of Cantú; success of dance reported in papers; Ley orgánica; Padre Catalán; Lagunillas; Larreátegui; Lacunza.
  - 4118 Durán, José María. Jonacatepec, May 2, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for military equipment to help maintain order; danger from Chiautla in Puebla.
  - 4119 Lagarde y Gassin (?), Javier. Tula, May 2, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Cases of cholera; danger to the troops; care of horses; plan for guarding the area.
  - 4120 Pérez Palacios, Ángel. Cuernavaca, May 3, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Opinion of Bustillos on income from tolls; Lacunza; Barrio; Medina; Lic. Aparicio; legislation on Cuernavaca; Goribar; Rovalo; road to Morelos; De la Trouplinière; road to Tenango and Ixtla; La Madrid; settlement of claims based on U.S. occupation.
  - 4121 Gómez, Tiburcio. San Gaspar, May 3, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for approval of payment of $1,000 to the Ayuntamiento de Jiutepec out of property debt; appointment to Road commission; road from Cuernavaca to Mexico; Ángel.
  - 4122 Iturbe, Francisco. Mexico, May 3, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Approval of decree lowering salaries of state employees; reduction in number of deputies and employees; tolls; credit for Federico Segovia; road to Tepeji.
  - 4123 Ceballos, Juan B. Morelia, May 3, 1850. ALS. 2 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Progress of the cholera; cures; Zitácuaro; prohibition of pulque, charape, and chicha, fish, fresh vegetables, pork; difficulties in enforcing the regulations.
  - 4124 Bassoco, José María de. Mexico, May 4, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Reduction of expenses; personal contribution; the Temis article; comparison by Marqués de Apantada between bureaucracy and the dropsy; similar problem of Jiménez de Cisneros; his religious policy; Chimborazo; Ixtaccihuatl; Sierra Nevada; comparison with U.S. policy.
  - 4125 Sein, Antonio. Tula, May 4, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Claim by Adrián Colina for reembursement for weapons furnished soldiers; support by Rafael María Villagrán and Ignacio Gutiérrez, ex-prefectos. Includes copy of printed Decree No. 108:
    - a. Congreso del Estado de México: [Decreto N. 108.] Toluca, January 8, 1849. Limited powers and rights of public officers. Original signed: José María Romero Díaz, Antonio Escudero, Manuel Guerra. Promulgated Toluca, January 9, 1849. Originally signed Pascual González Fuentes (Secretario de gobierno) and Mariano Arizcorreta (Governor).
  - 4126 Barrientos, José María. Mexico, May 4, 1850. ALS. 2 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Progress of the epidemic; opposition to public measures taken which interfere with Church operations; interference of ayuntamientos in Church affairs; processions; comparison with custom in Protestant countries.
  - 4127 Godoy, José María. Mexico, May 4, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Approval of Legislature's decision regarding the Mackintosh case; Manuelita.
  - 4128 Navarro, Mariano. Jilotepec, May 4, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm., 2 l. 13 × 21 cm.
    Progress of the epidemic; raíz del indio used as medicine; death of Otero. Transmits enclosed letter:
    - a. Acurin (?) [Cervantes]: [Carta a Navarro.] Soyaniq[uilpa]n, June 4(!), 1850. 2 l. f. 3-4v. Recommendation for gathering of hierba; Espejo; experience with the medicine.
  - 4129 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, May 4, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letter-head.
    Efforts of dissidents in Toluca to upset the government, using recent decrees as an excuse; suspicions of Faustino Villalba, Manuel Arellano, Villaverde, and Gerardo Gómez near Cuernavaca; General Pérez Palacios.
  - 4130 Villaseñor, Alejandro. Cuernavaca, May 5, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Agreement with Ayuntamiento over sale of acatlanes; epidemic; refusal of doctors from Mexico to come; help of Felipe Neri del Barrio; problem of the Juez de Jonacatepec; reduction of state expenses.
  - 4131 Alcocer, Luis A. San Pablo, May 5, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for help in case of Dolores Bernal; distrust of Indians for legal agents.
  - 4132 Herrera y Campos, Francisco. Texcoco, May 5, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Receipt of new orders; recipes for medicine; Junta de caridad; lack of funds for troops; equipment borrowed from Córdoba; rumors of Beltrán's new conspiracy; Chávez; Oliveros.
  - 4133 Villar, José del. Coyoacán, May 6, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Collection of toll; Ley de economías published in El Universal; León; the epidemic.
  - 4134 Cruz, Agustín. Mexico, May 6, 1850. ALS., 3 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Receipt of $800 from Mier for stagecoaches; San Juan; Zurutuza; Pascual González; business with Iturbe finished; Calle de Plateros; El Borrego; incident involving Frenchmen; Zaganta; approval of new laws; Noriega; Tulancingo; Romero; public security at Tlalpam; need for weapons; Lagarde guards at Tula; Escudero.
  - 4135 Copca, Bernardo. Mexico, May 6, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Collection of grain; Prefecto de Tula in Mixquiahuala; Hacienda de los Pozos; Gutiérrez Estrada's travels in Paris and Rome, leaving affairs to Copca; Hacienda de Ulapa, owned by María de Jesús Gómez de la Cortina, operated by Manuel Arena; Gil.
  - 4136 Arévalo Horcasitas, Luis. Tlayacapa[n], May 7, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Personal contribution; public instruction; payments for school for children in Tlayacapa[n], Atlatlahuca, San José, Santa Catarina, and San Andrés; illness of Alcalde primero.
  - 4137 Villaseñor, Alejandro. Cuernavaca, May 8, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Difficulties with Silva in the Ayuntamiento; release of Salgado.
  - 4138 Andrade, Cristóbal. Huejutla, May 8, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Tax collection in Sahuatlipan, Carpinteros, and Molango; disagreement with Administrador de Zacualtipán; Partidos de Zacualtipán and Metztitlán.
  - 4139 Carrión, José. Mexico, May 8, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Objections to marriage of son Gabriel Carrión to Concepción Valenzuela.
  - 4140 Barrio, Juan N. del. Mexico, May 8, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Plan for collection of taxes approved by Luis P[érez] Palacios; Ángel; service on Road Commission; Junta de Cuernavaca; work at Cuesta de Huichilaco; Becerril; tolls; Bustillos; Carlos Medina.
  - 4141 Cervantes, Miguel. Mexico, May 8, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Decree on salaries; road to Texcoco to be paid for by tolls; lack of confidence in Riva Palacio's tenure; new Department of Agriculture in San Gregorio.
  - 4142 Villar, José del. San Ángel, May 10, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 22 × 28 cm.
    Plan for repair of convents: Convento de Salvatierra at Colegio de San Ángel; opposition of Padre Provincial.
  - 4143 Iturbe, Francisco. Mexico, May 10, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Road-building program; gambling in Tlalpam.
  - 4144 [Carta anónima.] Toluca, May 10, 1850., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Lic. José Ramón Pacheco accused of organizing a pro-Santa Anna uprising; charges against Antonio Escudero, Remigio Mateos, Tiburcio Arce, José María Mateos, José Vicente González, Ignacio and Joaquín Valdés, Juan Fonseca, Felipe Sánchez Solís, and Ignacio Ramírez, with help of 1600 Indians from Metepec and Calisera (?) led by Cristóbal Jiménez and Pablo Gómez; weapons; meeting at house of Antonio Escudero; arrival of two generals.
  - 4145 Cueva, Ramón de la. Mexico, May 11, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Payments to Señora Soto requested by Salonio; Agustín Cruz; Señora Bouc (?); agreement with Señora Saldaña in 1849; approach of epidemic; meetings at San Vicente de Paul; Tenancingo.
  - 4146 Silva, Ignacio. Cuernavaca, May 11, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Alejandro Villaseñor.
  - 4147 Herrera, José Joaquín de. Mexico, May 11, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Recommendation for Br. José María Ordóñez.
  - 4148 Pérez Palacios, Ángel. Cuernavaca, May 11, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Lic. Alejandro Villaseñor recommended for place on the Tribunal Superior.
  - 4149 Haro y Tamariz, Antonio de. Mexico, May 11, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Purchase of interest in Mina de Veta Grande; Junta Directiva: Guillermo Drusina, Manuel Fiya y Cosío, and Felipe Neri del Barrio; Mineral de Guadalupe; transmittal of leaflet describing the company; Antonino, Doloritas, and Gregorio Mier.
  - 4150 Arrillaga, Basilio José. Mexico, May 11, 1850. LS., 2 l. 19 × 25 cm.
    Work on collection of laws and decrees since 1821; publication for 1828-1838 suspended for lack of funds; Arancel último de Aduanas marítimas; regulations of the aduanas with index; publication of volumes for 1849 and 1850; collection of Galván; subscription solicited.
  - 4151 Zurutuza, Anselmo. Mexico, May 12, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Transmittal of letter from Sargento Lara and recommendation; services guarding road from Venta de Córdoba to Río Frío. Includes draft of letter to Zurutuza, May 13, 1850, acknowledging receipt.
  - 4152 Almonte, Juan Nepomuceno. Mexico, May 12, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Alejandro Villaseñor to place on the Tribunal Superior; transmittal of copies of his own Memoria.
  - 4153 Rovalo, Luis. Santa Inés, May 12, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Meeting of the Junta de Cuernavaca to pass on new laws from the capital; notice by Aparicio; Goribar; Cortina; García; opposition to the new law; traffic on Mexico-Acapulco road insufficient to pay for building it.
  - 4154 Pérez Palacios, Ángel. Cuernavaca, May 12, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Letter of Lacunza; Ramal de Santiago; toll on Huitzilac Road; meeting with Aparicio; Morelos; Acapulco-Mexico Road; Carlos Medina; Barrio; Rovalo; Goribar; roads to Tenango and Tixtla; De La Trouplinière.
  - 4155 Sánchez Munive, Joaquín. Yautepec, May 12, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Use of raíz del indio in Morelia against the cholera; Santiago; sanitary precautions; Leonardo de la Puente.
  - 4156 Rebollar, Antonio. Texcoco, May 12, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Capture of Luis Espinoza; robbery at Tepetlaoxtoc; release under bond by José Antonio Palomo; search for Beltrán; Hacienda de San Antonio; Tonchonita.
  - 4157 Villar, José del. Coyoacán, May 13, 1850. LS., 1 l. 22 × 28 cm.
    Gambling at Tlalpam; Agustín Noriega; law reducing salaries of state employees; Aguirre; Los Carmelitos.
  - 4158 Escudero, P[edro]. Coyoacán, May 13, 1850. ALS., 3 l. 13 × 21 cm.
    Meeting in Cuernavaca; brandy tax; tax collection; powers of the Legislature.
  - 4159 Barrientos, José María. Mexico, May 13, 1850. ALS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Recommendation for Presbítero Manuel Perfecto Ordóñez, Cura interino de Apam.
  - 4160 Noriega, A[gustín]. Mexico, May 13, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Gambling and sedition in Tlalpam; Lic. Francisco Barrera's leaflets; difficulty of getting doctors in Tlalpam; Joaquín; absence of epidemic in Mexico and Tlalnepantla.
  - 4161 Barrientos, José María. [Mexico,] May 14, 1850. ALS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Recommendation for Lic. Francisco Zúñiga for the Tribunal superior.
  - 4162 Navarro, Mariano. Jilotepec, May 14, 1850. LS., 5 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Transmittal of brief of legal action between himself and the Tercera Sala del Tribunal.
    - a. Tercera Sala del Superior Tribunal: [Auto contra Blas Romero por injurias.] Toluca, April 27, 1850. f. 2. Fine of one day's pay against the Juez de Jilotepec under law of January 23, 1847. Marginal note, April 13, 1850 orders case forwarded; signed: Navarro to Ignacio Castro and José María Gelista; Jesús Uribe.
    - b. Joaquín de Mier: [Auto.] Toluca, April 29, 1850. f. 2. Returned for certification; original signed Gómez Eguiarte, José Montemo, and Montiel.
    - c. Navarro: [Auto.] Jilotepec, May 13, 1850. f. 2-3v. Review of case and precedents under law of January 23, 1847, and March 24, 1813; case against José Manuel for assault and robbery, against Gerónimo Juan for murder and robbery, against José Albino for assault and robbery, against Guadalupe Gil for robbery, against Pedro Rangel, Félix Juárez for robbery; certifications by Escribano Manuel Zomera y Piña.
    - d. [Blas Romero:] [Deposición.] Jilotepec, May 14, 1850. Copy. f. 4-5. Protest against application of law of April 13, 1849; ignorance of the law pleaded.
  - 4163 Lacunza, José María de. Mexico, May 15, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Letter of thanks for nomination to the Tribunal Superior; earlier experience with Arizcorreta.
  - 4164 [Herederos de María Dolores Trujano.] Tasacion hecha por los que suscribimos, en la Casa y esquina de la casablanca, de la Señora Doña María Dolores Trujano, á pedimento de los herederos, hoy día 15 de Mayo del año de 1850. Unsigned., 1 l. 21 × 31 cm.
    Inventory of furniture; value: $1,131.5.
  - 4165 Malo, José Ramón. Mexico, May 15, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Premature revolt in Puebla May 11; shortage of workers in road construction; return of Bonifacio Gutiérrez to the Ministry of Hacienda; interview with Baranda sought by MacKintosh; discussions with Bocanegra.
  - 4166 Rovalo, Luis. Santa Inés, May 16, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Discussion of projected law speeded by scheduled end of session for the Legislature; Aparicio; Goribar; Cortina; García; approval of the measure; co-operation between the state government and district juntas.
  - 4167 García, Fernando. Cuernavaca, May 16, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for appointment as judge; review of service as Juez de Apam, Tenancingo, Ixtlahuaca, and Cuernavaca; Abogado de pobres “de la Antigua Audiencia” and before the Tribunal Superior; earlier application to Arizcorreta for Juzgado de Zumpango; letter from Cayetano Ibarra.
  - 4168 Galicia, Faustino. Mexico, May 17, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for government position.
  - 4169 Flores, José María. Mexico, May 17, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Suit for recovery of alcabala; blame placed on Administrador de contribuciones de Zumpango.
  - 4170 Iturbe, Francisco. Mexico, May 17, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Inland road from Mexico reported shorter via Tepeji than through Tula and Huehuetoca; preference charged to local influence; use of road toll; advice of Marín Cervantes; personal interest disclaimed; opposition to Riva Palacio in Tlalpam; gambling allowed in Tacubaya.